<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The crafty maid's approbation: wherein she shews with black or brown; 'tis mony makes them straight go down; when pretty girls that gold has none, their fortune is still to lie alone.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690-1998?</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B02460</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6778</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide C.20.f.8[97]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99887668</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99887668</idno>
            <idno type="VID">183290</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B02460)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 183290)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; A5:2[81])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The crafty maid's approbation: wherein she shews with black or brown; 'tis mony makes them straight go down; when pretty girls that gold has none, their fortune is still to lie alone.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill. (woodcuts).  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by and for W.O. A.M. and sold by C. Bates, at the Bible and Sun in Pye-corner.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[not before 1690]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Verse: "Draw near to me young girls to side ..."</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Trimmed.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ballads, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="ballad">
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:183290:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 1 -->
            <head>The Crafty MAID's APPROBATION:</head>
            <argument>
               <l>Wherein ſhe ſhews either Black or Brown,</l>
               <l>'Tis Mony makes them ſtraight go down;</l>
               <l>When pretty Girls that Gold has none,</l>
               <l>Their fortune is ſtill to lie alone.</l>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>DRaw near to me young Girls ſo fine,</l>
               <l>Whoſe means and portion's like to mine:</l>
               <l>If you'll but hear what I have pen'd,</l>
               <l>'Twill make you ſmile before I end:</l>
               <l>I once had Sweet-hearts fair and young,</l>
               <l>Tho' now from me he's fled and gone;</l>
               <l>But I'll tell you a very good reaſon why,</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>'Twas Mony did part my Love and I.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When firſt to me a wooing h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> came,</l>
               <l>He <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id deſire to know my name;</l>
               <l>I told him my portion it was but ſmall,</l>
               <l>He ſaid he valued none at all:</l>
               <l>So that my favour he could win,</l>
               <l>He valued nothing elſe a pin;</l>
               <l>But now he's gone and I kn<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w not why,</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>'Twas mony,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet for three years his love ſtood faſt,</l>
               <l>And he vow'd for ever it ſhould laſt:</l>
               <l>But when my Friends ſpoke of the ſame,</l>
               <l>Then he was for another Dame;</l>
               <l>Except ſo much mony they'd give me,</l>
               <l>No Wif for him I muſt not be:</l>
               <l>His words he clearly did deny,</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>So mony did part my Love and I.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus Maids may ſee, ſo may I too,</l>
               <l>It is for mony young Men wooe:</l>
               <l>A great deal of love they will pretend,</l>
               <l>But mark what falls out in the end;</l>
               <l>When they find your portions are but ſmall,</l>
               <l>Like to a ſnake from you they'll crawl;</l>
               <l>And to another ſtraight they'll hye,</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>So mony did part,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If I had a head like a horſe,</l>
               <l>Or a body as thick as a mill-poſt;</l>
               <l>So bags came but tumbling in,</l>
               <l>Then my favour every Fool wou'd win;</l>
               <l>Or was I long ſnouted like a ſow,</l>
               <l>Or elſe crook-backt like our fine cow:</l>
               <l>Have at her then, theſe Boys would cry,</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>She's mony enough, and what care I.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Young Men don't bluſh, you know 'tis true,</l>
               <l>For let her name be <hi>Mary</hi> or <hi>Sue;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Tho' ſhe was blabber-lipt, alſo blear-ey'd,</l>
               <l>Yet mony all thoſe faults will hide;</l>
               <l>Nay, where ſhe the naſti<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt dingieſt Slut,</l>
               <l>That a Man durſt not after her crack a nut;</l>
               <l>Had ſhe but mony, houſe, or land,</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>I'm ſure ſhe would not ſtick long a hand.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet we whoſe portions are but ſmall,</l>
               <l>Let us not be diſmaid at all:</l>
               <l>Neither let us grieve, lament, nor ſwound,</l>
               <l>For beauty's worth a thouſand pound</l>
               <l>Hang't, though my firſt true Love be gone,</l>
               <l>I've the ſame face for another Man;</l>
               <l>And i'll prove honeſt till I dye,</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>Though mony did part,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If two young Men talk of a Wench,</l>
               <l>As they do ſit on an Ale-bench;</l>
               <l>She's a Good-huſwife, the one replyes;</l>
               <l>But has ſhe mony? the other cries:</l>
               <l>If ſhe has none ſhe's not for me,</l>
               <l>Give me the caſh, hang huſwifery,</l>
               <l>I love to finger that, for why,</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>'Tis mony did part,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>By this young Girls may plainly ſee,</l>
               <l>How deceitful theſe young Men be;</l>
               <l>They'll ſearch a Maid from top to toe,</l>
               <l>Till all her ſecrets they do know;</l>
               <l>Then if her means don't pleaſe his mind,</l>
               <l>He quickly can turn like the wind:</l>
               <l>I muſt have a Wife with more, he'll cry,</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>So mony,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Such affection did that young Man bear,</l>
               <l>That he often called me his Dear:</l>
               <l>Such vows and oaths he made, 'tis known,</l>
               <l>But now he doth them quite diſown:</l>
               <l>But ſince he's gone, ſing farewel he,</l>
               <l>I'll ſlight him more than he does me;</l>
               <l>I'll ne'r lament, nor weep, nor cry,</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>Though mony did part,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I am full glad we parted in truth,</l>
               <l>For ſince I hear he's a croſs-grain'd Youth;</l>
               <l>But had he prov'd true, though ne'r ſo bare,</l>
               <l>In wealth or woe i'd dare a <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>re;</l>
               <l>But now i'm free, i'll let that ſlide,</l>
               <l>And ne'r think more to be a Bride:</l>
               <l>There's nothing like to liberty,</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>Since mony did part,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus have I told young Maidens all,</l>
               <l>How the weakeſt go to the wall;</l>
               <l>But ſhe that is full and her purſe well ſtrung,</l>
               <l>She ſhall have Sweet-hearts come ding dong:</l>
               <l>It's no matter for breeding or ſence,</l>
               <l>So ſhe has but caſh, he'll have the Wench;</l>
               <l>Black or brown, he looks not o' t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>' dye,</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>'Twas mony did part my Love and I.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <p>Licens'd and Enter'd according to Order.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed by and for <hi>W. O. A. M.</hi> and ſold by <hi>C. Bates.</hi> at the Bible and Sun in <hi>Pye-corner.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
